AMMAR AZIZ

BRISBANE, QLD 4030 • AMMAR.AZIZ@MENZIES.EDU.AU • 0488 055 307

SUMMARY

Bioinformatics PhD candidate (submitted) at Menzies School of Health Research with four years experience as a Research Assistant in molecular microbiology. Proficient in NGS, bioinformatics, phylogenomics, transcriptomics and extensive experience programming (Python, R, Bash) and statistics.

EXPERIENCE

PhD Candidate (Full-Time)

MENZIES SCHOOL HEALTH RESEARCH, CHARLES DARWIN UNIVERSITY

Jan 2016 – Jan 2020 Brisbane, QLD

- Proficient in phylogenomic reconstruction and analysis (PAUP*, RAxML, FastTree).
- WGS and RNAseq to characterise the bacterial human pathogens B. pseudomallei and H. influenzae.
- MLST and genomics for point-source tracing and geographic attribution.
- Extensive knowledge of bacterial genetics and molecular microbiology.
- Proficient in CLI and HPC for analysis of large biological datasets.
- Extensive use and proficiency in Python, R and Bash.
- Developed in-house pipelines for bacterial mixture analysis, variant calling in polyploidy samples.
- Extensive use of current-generation aligners (Bowtie2, BWA-MEM, STAR and Kalisto) for analysis of prokaryotic (including viruses) and eukaryotic organisms.
- Extensive use of GATK toolkit for variant calling, VCF manipulation, processing and filtering.
- Experience in a broad range of bioinformatics tools for genomic data analysis and visualisation.
- Trained colleagues in NGS bioinformatics analysis using HPC environment.
- Authored three first-author peer-reviewed articles and collaborated on further two publications.

Research Assistant (Full-Time)

MENZIES SCHOOL OF HEALTH RESEARCH, CHARLES DARWIN UNIVERSITY

Jan 2013 – Dec 2015 Darwin, NT

- Performed high-throughput assays for detection, species determination, genotyping of Malaria samples
- High-throughput analysis of sanger sequencing using UGENE software suite.
- Designed and optimised in-house PCR assays for species-specific amplification of microsatellites and for human haplotype SNP detection using restriction length fragment polymorphism.
- Coordination and processing of high-throughput processing of plasma samples for HPLC analysis.
- Worked with clinicians, nurses to organise specimens for analysis and communicated results effectively
- Trained several international collaborators in specimen processing and malaria speciation assays
- Organised biobank for international shipping, long term storage, retrieval and tracking.
- Creation and management of databases in Microsoft Excel and Access.
- Fire Warden and OH&S member for the laboratory.

Research Assistant (Full-Time)

JAMES COOK UNIVERSITY, QUEENSLAND TROPICAL HEALTH ALLIANCE

Jan 2010 – Jun 2012 Cairns, QLD

- Operated and maintained a MALDI TOF/TOF and Shimadzu Prominence Nanoflow LC/Nano spotter for mass spectrometry protein analysis.
- Maintained and operated an applied Biosystems QSTAR Elite LCMS System.
- Prepared hundreds of in-house and external protein samples using mass spectrometry in support of Proteomic and Bioinformatics research in collaboration with internal and external Scientists
- Trained students and staff on the use of OFF-GEL fractionators and mass spectrometers, as well as iTRAQ, and SDS-PAGE electrophoresis.
- Assisted researchers in experiments, including intraperitoneal and subcutaneous injection of samples into laboratory mice strains and harvesting animal tissue.

AMMAR AZIZ

BRISBANE, QLD 4030 • AMMAR.AZIZ@MENZIES.EDU.AU • 0488 055 307

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy Candidate

MENZIES SCHOOL HEALTH RESEARCH, CHARLES DARWIN UNIVERSITY

• Thesis: "Genomic and transcriptomic characterisation of the human pathogens *B. pseudomallei* and *H. influenzae*"

Submitted: Jan 2020 Brisbane, QLD

Bachelor of Science, Microbiology (Honours)

JAMES COOK UNIVERSITY

• Thesis: "Proteomic characterisation of the hookworm secretome"

Graduated: Jul 2012 Cairns, QLD

Bachelor of Science, Microbiology

University of Queensland

Graduated: Feb 2010 Brisbane, QLD

AWARDS & PRESENTATIONS

Awards

Microbe Conference Travel Award (2019) ASM Tri-State Finalist (2017) UQ Winter School Travel Bursary (2016) ICHEAR CRE Top-up Scholarship (2016) Australian Postgraduate Award (PhD) (2016)

Conferences

Microbe San Francisco Poster and Fire Talk (2019) ASM Brisbane - Poster (2018) ASM Hobart - Oral Presentation (2017) UQ Winter School in Math. & Comp. Biology (2016)

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Full publication list available at www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=ammar+aziz

- Aziz A, Currie BJ, Mayo M, Sarovich DS, Price EP. Comparative genomics confirms a rare melioidosis human-to-human transmission event and reveals incorrect phylogenomic reconstruction due to polyclonality (2020) Microbial Genomics.
- Aziz A, Sarovich DS, Nosworthy E, Bleissbarth J, Chang AB, Smith-Vaughn H, Harris TM & Price EP.
 Molecular Signatures of Non-typeable Haemophilus influenzae Lung Adaptation in Pediatric Chronic Lung Disease (2019)
 Frontiers in Microbiology.
- Phillips S, Quigley BL, Aziz A, Bergen W, Booth R, Pyne M, Timms P. Antibiotic treatment of Chlamydia-induced cystitis in the koala is linked to expression of key inflammatory genes in reactive oxygen pathways (2019) PLoS One.
- Aziz A, Sarovich DS, Harris TM, Kaestli M, McRobb E, Mayo M, Currie BJ, Price EP. Suspected cases of
 intracontinental Burkholderia pseudomallei sequence type homoplasy resolved using whole-genome sequencing (2017) Microbial
 Genomics.
- Olagoke O, Quigley BL, Aziz A, Phillips S, Booth R, Timms P. Transcriptome profile of koala peripheral blood mononuclear cells in response to vaccination against koala retrovirus. (In press, 2019) Viruses

BIOINFORMATICS SKILLS AND SOFTWARE

- Short-Read Aligners: BWA-MEM, Bowtie2, STAR, Kallisto
- Phylogeny reconstruction: PAUP*, RAxML, FastTree
- NGS tools: SAMtools, bedtools, GATK4, BLAST+, MAFFT
- Assembly: metaSPAdes/SPAdes, Velvet
- Misc: BUSCO, fastp, edgeR, NextFlow, MetaPhlan2 suite
- Databases: NCBI, KEGG, Uniprot, GO, Ensembl Genomes, GISAID EpiFlu
- Extensive knowledge of Linux, Bash scripting, and schedulers
- Expert in data cleaning, scraping, processing, visualisation and statistical analysis in R

REFERENCES

Ass. Prof. Erin Price

SENIOR RESEARCH FELLOW
University of Sunshine Coast
E: eprice@usc.edu.au

P: 07 5456 5568

Dr. Tegan Harris

SENIOR RESEARCH OFFICER
Defence Science and Technology
Tegan.harris@dst.defence.gov.au
0410 695 394

Dr. Derek Sarovich

SENIOR RESEARCH FELLOW University of Sunshine Coast dsarovich@usc.edu.au 07 5456 3748